<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Gaming, Computing, and Physics</title><link href="https://lamberss.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://lamberss.github.io/feeds/gaming.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://lamberss.github.io/</id><updated>2015-02-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>Solitaire RPG Experiment</title><link href="https://lamberss.github.io/posts/2015/02/solitaire-rpg-experiment" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-02-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Steven E. Lamberson Jr.</name></author><id>tag:lamberss.github.io,2015-02-13:posts/2015/02/solitaire-rpg-experiment</id><summary type="html">
&lt;img alt="" class="align-left" src="https://lamberss.github.io/images/dice_and_sheets.jpg" style="width: 150px;"/&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="when-addicitons-aren-t-fed"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id1"&gt;When Addicitons Aren't Fed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love playing tabletop, pen-and-paper role-playing games (RPGs).  In fact, I
don't think it would be a stretch to say that playing them is my favorite
pass time by a significant margin.  While I only have experience with several
versions of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dnd.wizards.com"&gt;Dungeons &amp;amp; Dragons&lt;/a&gt; (D&amp;amp;D) and the closely-related &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paizo.com/Pathfinder"&gt;Pathfinder&lt;/a&gt;
games, I think it is fair to say that I would like any RPG fairly well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, as they say, am addicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, due to changes in my personal life, I have been unable to play.
While I do not regret the change in my personal life, and I would not change it
if I could, I do miss my favorite pass time.  My group should be getting started
again in the next few weeks, but everyone is busy so the start date is later
than I would want.  So, I started looking for ways to feed my addiction given
the constraints of my new life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="asynchronous-rpgs"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id2"&gt;Asynchronous RPGs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a way to play games known as "play-by-post" (PbP).  It can be applied
to most board games, and there are several communities on the internet devoted
to playing RPGs in this fashion (such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.myth-weavers.com"&gt;myth-weavers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.thetangledweb.net"&gt;thetangledweb&lt;/a&gt;).
In theory it is similar to playing face-to-face at a table, and like any
alternative to anything there are a number of pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asynchronous&lt;/strong&gt; - You are not playing at the same time, so it is easier to
schedule.  Instead of blocking out several hours each week to play (and
several more to plan if you are the game master), you can spend several
minutes a day making your one or two posts for that day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved role-playing&lt;/strong&gt; - Because you have more time to think about your
role-playing responses, it is easier to incorporate your character's back story
and motivations into your actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved tactical play&lt;/strong&gt; - Because you have more time to think about your
tactical responses, it is easier to make tactically superior choices (or
to make tactically inferior choices that are &lt;em&gt;in character&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved writing skills&lt;/strong&gt; - You have to describe everything using words.
You cannot mime or make sound effects (although you can link pictures or
sound-bites, I suppose).  This turns into a lot of practice writing, which
turns into better writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pace&lt;/strong&gt; - Even if you have a pace of two posts per day (aggressive by
PbP standards), your game will still take forever to play.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encumbered social interactions&lt;/strong&gt; - Out-of-character (OOC) conversations are
harder to have, and they are not real time, and this is a major drawback.  No
one else will get excited and jump out of their chair when you land that
massive crit, or moan in despair when you miss on a key roll, or laugh like
crazy when you come up with that really witty retort.  And even if they do
these things, you won't know because you aren't there with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encumbered tactical play&lt;/strong&gt; - Tactical play can be encumbered for several
reasons.  Perhaps the biggest one is that the game master will not be able
to update the tactical grid between each player's turn, so it is possible
that the thing you say you are attacking when your turn comes around is
already dead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I am an aspiring author (or, rather, I aspire to be an aspiring author),
so the "Improved writing skills" idea is very appealing to me.  I definitely
don't think I will ever prefer PbP to playing face-to-face, but I do think it
might be appealing enough to be worth investigating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I decided to try to get into a game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="mama-someone-on-the-internet-was-mean-to-me"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id3"&gt;Mama, someone on the internet was mean to me!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I started keeping tabs on the "Looking for Games" forum on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.thetangledweb.net"&gt;thetangledweb&lt;/a&gt;.
After a few days I found a post for someone wanting to start a D&amp;amp;D 5e game.
The GM was a site moderator, so I figured she would be pretty good.  (I don't
know her gender, and her username is androgynous, but for some reason I think
of her as a girl.)  I made up a quick character concept and got pulled into
the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character I came up with was named Casseph "Mad Cass" Thorald, and he was
a half-elf wild magic sorcerer that was more than a little insane.  I was
excited!  I waited patiently for the game to start, checking the forum several
times a day every day for a week.  I started to feel let down, but then I did
some more poking around and found out that the game had started several days
ago and somehow I hadn't been notified.  Oh No!!!!!  Total rookie mistake.
Anyway, I made my post and got my character caught back up.  I was totally
stoked.  "I'm playing D&amp;amp;D!"  I was thinking to myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I waited.  And waited.  And waited.  Another week goes by and there
are no more posts to the game.  I am more savvy with the forum so I know I did
not miss a post (unless the game moved to a private area and I was deliberately
excluded).  Furthermore, I can click on the GM's name and see that she hasn't
posted anything anywhere on the entire site since the last time she posted in
my game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has now been two weeks with no signs of activity from the GM, and no word
about where she has gone or when she is coming back.  Internet anonymity
strikes again!  I find myself wondering what happened to her.  Did she get
killed, or arrested?  I don't know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sad thing is that this was not my first delve into PbP, but my first
attempt ended just as abruptly (although I had posted three or four times
before that one died).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusion - Do not rely on systems with internet anonymity to provide a
necessary service, like feeding a gaming addiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="if-you-want-it-done-right-you-have-to-do-it-yourself"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id4"&gt;If you want it done right, you have to do it yourself.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here I am, wallowing in the misery that is not playing my beloved RPGs.  I
cannot get a real-life game going any quicker than it will get going because I
have to wait till everyone else is ready to game.  I cannot get a PbP game
going because I don't want to run my own game until I have played in one so I
can get a better estimate of how big of a time commitment it is, and I have to
wait for yet another game to get started by someone else that I don't know and
who will likely abandon me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I need to play RIGHT NOW!  Too bad I can't play by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or can I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What would it be like if I played in my own PbP game?  We now have
a new alternative, so let's look at the pros and cons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pros:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything happens on &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; schedule&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everything is orchestrated by one mind, so there is no game timing conflict.
I don't have to worry about taking my turn out of order because all of the
turns are my turn.  This should make the game run much more like a &lt;strong&gt;real
novel&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I get to control all the characters, so I can explore stories where only
one of them is the main character instead of all of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All the pros for normal PbPs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;no surprises&lt;/strong&gt;, at least not in story elements.  There will be
minor surprises due to randomness, but I will see every single plot-twist
coming and I will know all the stats of all the monsters as I am fighting
them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As with normal PbPs, there is a lack of social interaction compared to
face-to-face games.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally don't think I will mind the cons that much, especially if I am
getting my social needs met in other venues.  But did you see the second pro?
It will look more like a &lt;strong&gt;real novel&lt;/strong&gt;.  And did you remember what I said
earlier?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I am an aspiring author (or, rather, I aspire to be an aspiring author)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons that I just aspire to be an aspiring author is that I keep
getting stuck because I don't know what to write about.  In fact, I have two
very specific sources of writer's block: I have trouble deciding names for
things and I have trouble writing about plots that I haven't fully thought
through (but I cannot fully think them through until I have written about them).
If I am running myself through a pre-made RPG module or adventure path, then I
am guaranteed not to run into either of these problems because all the people,
places, and things will already have names (except the main characters, but
that's a one-time cost) and the plot is already outlined in the adventure path.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You mean I get to play my beloved RPGs &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; get practice writing all a the
same time?  Yes, please!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="remember-the-word-experiment"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a class="toc-backref" href="#id5"&gt;Remember the word "experiment"?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, now that you understand the hypothesis, I will explain the experiment.  I
will be running myself through the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paizo.com/Pathfinder"&gt;Pathfinder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Kingmaker&lt;/em&gt; adventure path, at
least up through the first several encounters.  I have chosen &lt;em&gt;Kingmaker&lt;/em&gt;
because I already own all I need to do to do it, and I am already familiar
with the story because I have been a GM for a &lt;em&gt;Kingmaker&lt;/em&gt; campaign before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully I will enjoy myself.  Who knows?  Clearly I cannot publish anything
I write based on modules and adventure paths written by others, but maybe I
will be able to take this framework and apply it to my own content in order
to actually start writing that book I've been thinking about for almost 20
years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</summary><category term="d&amp;d"></category><category term="myth-weavers"></category><category term="Pathfinder"></category><category term="rpg"></category><category term="thetangledweb"></category></entry></feed>